<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	version="5.0"
	
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Multiple Document Types</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>When a system needs to represent a range of different document types, each document
				type can be represented by a completely separate declarations.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>A system needs to represent different types of information. This information may be
			used at different times, or may be used by different parts of the system.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>Systems which need to represent a variety of information at different times or
			places.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>Processing and authoring of documents can be simplified if different document types
			are used to represent different sets of data.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Use different document types to represent different sets of data within the
			system.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>
		<para>In a payroll system, data about the Employees, and data about the hours they work can
			be represented by separate documents.</para>

		<example>
			<title>Employees.dtd:</title>

			<programlisting language="dtd"><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT Employee (Name, HourlyRate)>
<!ATTLIST Employee id ID #REQUIRED>

<!ELEMENT Name (#PCDATA)>

<!ELEMENT HourlyRate (#PCDATA)>
			]]></programlisting>
		</example>


		<example>
			<title>HoursWorked.dtd:</title>

			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT PayPeriod (Employee+)>
<!ATTLIST PayPeriod
StartDate #CDATA
EndDate   #CDATA>

<!ELEMENT Employee (HoursWorked)>
<!ATTLIST Employee id NMTOKEN>

<!ELEMENT HoursWorked (#PCDATA)>
			]]></programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>


	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>If different people will authoring the different types of documents it is a good idea
			to have completely separate document types, because authors will not need to be exposed
			to parts of the document types that are not needed.</para>
		<para>Having separate document types allows the different DTDs to be versioned
			independently.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para><link xl:href="/patterns/doc-roots/universal-root.xml">Universal Root</link> allows multiple types of data under one document root. Multi Root
			Document Types allows for multiple types of documents to be declared in a single
			declaration.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>
		<para>…</para>
	</section>
</section>
