<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	
	version="5.0"
    xreflabel="Container Element"
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Container Element</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>A container has multiple elements as child elements. A new element type is created to
				group related elements. This is a very general pattern and many other patterns
				specialize this one.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>There are multiple elements that occur at the same level within a document. These
			elements can be separated into distinct groups.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>There are multiple elements that can occur as child elements of a single, higher level
			element, and some of these elements are related.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>Documents need structure, and this is the easiest way to add structure to a
			document.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Create a new element that contains some of the multiple child elements.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>


		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<ComputerConfiguration>
	<RAM>128 MB</RAM>
	<WordProcessor>WordPerfect</WordProcessor>
	<HardDriveSize>8GB</HardDriveSize>
	<XMLParser>Xerces</XMLParser>
</ComputerConfiguration>
]]></programlisting>


		<para>The above document describes a computer’s configuration. If however processing
			software was only interested in the hardware aspects of the configuration it would need
			to check all of the elements and extract the RAM and <tag class="element">HardDriveSize</tag> elements. Compare
			this to the following:</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<ComputerConfiguration>
	<Software>
		<Wordprocessor>Wordperfect</Wordprocessor>
		<XMLParser>Xerces</XMLParser>
	</Software>
	<Hardware>
		<RAM>128 MB<RAM>
		<HardDriveSize>8 GB</HardDriveSize>
	</Hardware>
</ComputerConfiguration>
]]></programlisting>

		<para>In this example the software and hardware aspects of the configuration are separated.
			Processing software that need to extract individual aspects can do so easily.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>This pattern adds a level of abstraction to the structure of a document. This
			abstraction can be used to simply provide grouping of elements as in the Examples
			section. This grouping provides additional semantic information about the data.</para>
		<para>This extra element can also be a useful place to provide metadata about the individual
			group of data.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>

		<para>The <xref xl:href="/patterns/organization/marketplace.xml" /> pattern can be used if there is more than one category that can apply to each type.</para>
		<para>The <xref xl:href="/patterns/metadata/head-body.xml" /> pattern uses two specific types of Container Elements, one for metadata and one for content.</para>
		<para>The <tag class="element">Collection</tag> Element is a container for single type of element.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>
		<para>The Isogen whitepaper Object-Oriented SGML Deconstructing SGML for Storage Section
			contains an an excellent example of where a container was used to help in the storage
			and retrieval of data.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>References</title>

		<para>See Structuring XML Documents, Section 5.2.1: Containers.</para>
	</section>

</section>
