<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	
	version="5.0"
    xreflabel="Domain Element"
	role="pattern">

	<info>
		<title>Domain Element</title>
		
		<abstract>
			<para>A concept from domain analysis is made into an element.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>A concept in the domain needs to be recognized as a distinct unit of information when
			processing it.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>Every document has a domain, and every domain has unique concepts.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>Data needs to be structured in order to be processed.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Concepts from the domain become elements in the document.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>
		<para>In a payroll processing system, Employees, Hourly Wage, and Hours Worked are all
			concepts from the domain. These can all be made into elements in a document type used
			for dealing with the payroll.</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Employee id="62537">
	<HourlyWage>25.00</HourlyWage>
	<HoursWorked>40</HoursWorked>
</Employee>
		]]></programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>Object Oriented Analysis and Entity-Relational DataBase modeling techniques are useful
			for finding domain concepts.</para>
		<para>Granularity of object needs to be thought about. Too granular results in more markup
			and more processing, if elements are not granular enough, extra parsing needs to be done
			by the application.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>…</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>

		<para>All document types are full of Domain Elements.</para>
		<para><acronym>XHTML</acronym> is used for markup of documents to be displayed so it contains elements for
			things such as titles, headings, and paragraphs.</para>
		<para>The Information and Content Exchange (ICE) Protocol is used for distributing web
			content, so it contains elements such as sender, receiver, request and response.</para>
	</section>
</section>
