<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	
	version="5.0"
	xreflabel="Optional Container Element"
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Optional Container Element</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>When creating large DTDs with many logical units authors might be required to learn a
				large number of these logical units to know how to use the DTD. By hiding the details of
				optional parts of the DTD beneath optional elements, some of this complexity can be
				reduced.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>In a DTD with many logical units, an author of a document can be overwhelmed with the
			number of choices that have to be made.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>In large, general-purpose DTDs where many logical units are presented, and more than
			one of the units is optional. The document will be authored by humans.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>In order to make DTDs applicable in many situations, large numbers of logical units
			need to appear in the DTD. However, presenting large numbers of logical units makes the
			DTD more difficult to learn by authors of documents.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Hide related parts of a document that may never be needed by an author of a document
			beneath an element type. Any details of the structure of a document that are optional in
			a document can be grouped together as attributes and children elements of a single
			element. If an author never uses this branch of the document, none of the logical units
			within that branch need to be known to the other.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>

		<para>Let’s create a DTD that allows an author to create notes that can be a note to oneself, or an email. The DTD might look like this:</para>

		<programlisting language="dtd"><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT Note (NoteToSelf | Email )>
<!ELEMENT NoteToSelf (Body)>
<!ELEMENT Body (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT Email (Recipient+, CC*, BCC*, Body)>
<!ELEMENT Recipient (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT CC (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT BCC (#PCDATA)>
		]]></programlisting>

		<para>If the author of these documents only had to be create notes to himself, he would
			never need to be aware of the elements that are required in the <tag class="element">Email</tag> branch of the DTD.
			He would create his document like this:</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Note>
	<NoteToSelf>
		<Body>This is my note</Body>
	</NoteToSelf>
<Note>
		]]></programlisting>

		<para>Although the DTD contains 7 elements, the author would only have to use three
			elements: <tag class="element">Note</tag>, <tag class="element">NoteToSelf</tag> and <tag class="element">Email</tag>. The author would never be required to use the
			Email element and would not even have to be aware of the existence of the remaining
			three elements.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>Once the Optional Group Pattern is applied, the learning requirements placed on the
			author of documents is reduced. Application of this pattern can however lead to an
			increase in the overall number of logical units in the DTD. The above note DTD could
			have been written as follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="dtd"><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT Note (Recipient?, CC?, BCC?, Body)>
<!ELEMENT Body (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT Recipient (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT CC (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT BCC (#PCDATA)>
		]]></programlisting>


		<para>This actually reduces the number of logical units in the DTD from 7 to 5, but makes
			things more complicated for users who just want to write notes to themselves, because
			they now have to be aware of the <tag class="element">Recipient</tag>, <tag class="element">CC</tag>, and <tag class="element">BCC</tag> elements. 
		    The Optional Group hides complexity from the authors of documents by introducing optional elements that
			hide the details of a piece of the document that the author might not care about. By
			introducing a single higher level element, the details of many logical units may be
			hidden from the author, thereby reducing the learning requirements of the author.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>This Optional Group is similar to the <xref xl:href="choice-reducing-container.xml" /> 
		    in that they both hide logical units of a document from the author by introducing 
		    new element types. Existing elements are group together beneath the new element. 
		    The major difference between the two is the context they are used in. 
		    The Choice Group relates elements that are all choices in a content group while the 
		    Optional Group relates optional elements from the content group.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>

		<para>This DTD fragment was taken from XBEL:</para>

		<programlisting language="dtd"><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT xbel (title?, info?, desc?, (%nodes.mix;)*)>
<!ELEMENT info (metadata+)>
<!ELEMENT metadata EMPTY>
<!ATTLIST metadata owner CDATA #REQUIRED>
		]]></programlisting>

		<para>When generating an XBEL document, the info element is not required. This means that if
			the author was never interested in creating an info element, he would not need to know
			about the info element, the metadata element, or the owner attribute, thus eliminating 3
			logical units from what the author needs to learn.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Contributions</title>
		<para>Thanks to Pankaj Kamthan from Concordia University for fixing up a bit of XML in the pattern.</para>
	</section>
</section>
