<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	version="5.0"

	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Head-Body</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>When a large amount of metadata needs to be included in an element the designer may
				create two children for the element, one for the metadata and one for the body of the
				document.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>Sometimes, an element has a large amount of metadata, and this metadata may need to be
			structured. In common XML usage, attributes are used for metadata. But with a large
			amount of metadata it is difficult for authors to include this information within
			attributes, which have limited structure. Including metadata as sibling elements of
			content elements leads to the potential to confuse the metadata and the data meant to be
			in the body of the element.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>There is a large amount of metadata about some piece of content. For example
			information about the title, creation date, and authors of a document should be included
			with the document, but this is not really information that belong in the body of the
			document.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>A clear separation is needed between what is metadata and what is data that forms the
			body of the document. This affects ease of authoring and processing of the document
			because the context of the data is implied. The metadata needed for an element needs to
			structured in such a way that attributes are difficult to use.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>

		<para>Create <tag class="element">head</tag> and <tag class="element">body</tag> elements. The element that contains the head and body elements
			can be referred to as the skeleton element. The metadata for the document goes into the
			head element, and the data for the document itself goes into the body element. The XML
			takes the following form:</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Skeleton>
	<Head>
		… meta information …
	</Head>
	<Body>
		… body of document …
	</Body>
</Skeletion>
		]]></programlisting>
	</section>


	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Document>
	<Head>
		<Author>John Doe</Author>
		<Author>Frank Black</Author>
		<CreationDate>June 16, 1999</CreationDate>
	</Head>
	<Body>
		This is a document.
	</Body>
</Document>
		]]></programlisting>


		<para>In this case, the skeleton element is the document root, and the metadata is
			structured information about the authors of the document and the creation date of the
			document. The Head-Body pattern is often used at the document level, but it can also be
			used at levels deeper within a document. For example the pattern could be used inside of
			a Table element like this:</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Document>
	<Table>
		<TableHead>
			<Title>
			A <Italic>Sample<Italic> Table
			</Title>
		</TableHead>
		<TableBody>
			<Row>Row 1</Row>
			<Row>Row 2</Row>
		</TableBody>
	</Table>
</Document>
]]></programlisting>

		<para>In this case the skeleton element is a table, which needs structure for its Title
			data.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>Two new elements are introduced which distinguish the metadata from the body of the
			document. This gives processing software context to distinguish these two types of
			data.</para>
		<para>Because this introduced two additional elements, the resulting documents are larger
			than they would be without the application of this pattern</para>
		<para>The resulting documents are often easier to understand because of the clear separation
			of metadata and the document body itself. The metadata is in the Head element and the
			document itself goes in the Body element. Authors and processing software can clearly
			distinguish the context of the data they are using.</para>
		<para>Documents are also often easier to process because they allow metadata to be
			structured, unlike if attributes were use for the metadata of the document.</para>
		<para>For an interesting alternative, see Don Park’s “Neck” pattern.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>The Head-Body pattern consists of two new Container Elements added to the structure of
			the document, one for the Head element, and one for the Body. This is a specialization
			of the Separate Metadata and Data.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>

		<para>HEAD and BODY elements in XHTML.</para>
		<para>SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol) uses Header and Body Elements inside an <link xl:href="/patterns/organization/envelope.xml">Envelope</link>
			element.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>References</title>
		<para>Rick Jelliffe discusses this in a chapter entitled “The Document Shell” in:
			The XML &amp; SGML Cookbook: Recipes for Structured Information</para>
	</section>
</section>
