<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	
	version="5.0"
    xreflabel="Separate Metadata and Data"
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Separate Metadata and Data</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>When documents contain content and data about the content, the two types of data
				should be clearly separated.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>

		<para>A document contains two distinct types of data, the content of the document, and data
			about the content. The data about the content is referred to as metadata. Since a
			document contains these two different types of data, it is not always to distinguish
			between the two types of data. For example:</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<ArticleSummaries>
	<Author>Phred Smith</Author>
	<Name>Patterns of Stereo Design</Name>
	<Author>J.R. Dolby</Author>
	<Summary>
		Use of patterns to arrange stereo components.
	</Summary>
</ArticleSummary>
		]]></programlisting>

		<para>Here there are two instances of the <tag class="element">Author</tag> element, and at first glance it might not
			be possible to tell what the first instance of <tag class="element">Author</tag> represents. Is it the author of
			the article being summarized? Is it the author of the article itself? It can be
			difficult to distinguish metadata from data.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>Data about the data needs to be included in a document. This could be things like the
			author’s name, the creation date, security levels of the data, namespace
			information, schema information, or identification attributes for use with cross
			references.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>A clear separation is needed between what is metadata and what is data that forms the
			body of the document. This affects ease of authoring and processing of the document
			because the context of the data is clear.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>The context of the data and the metadata should be made clear. The metadata should
			usually appear before the data that it describes. This makes it clearer what the
			metadata is about, and allows processing software to know about the data before it
			actually gets the data. For example the size of a table might be considered metadata. If
			the processing software gets the size of the table before the actual data, it can layout
			the table and then insert the data in the proper place as it encounters it.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>
		<para>See the <link xl:href="/patterns/metadata/metadata-doc.xml">Metadata in Separate Document</link>, <link xl:href="/patterns/metadata/head-body.xml">Head-Body pattern</link>s for examples.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>
		<para>The resulting context provides structures that clearly identify the metadata as
			metadata. Often this pattern introduces new constructs to the document, so the overall
			length of the document may be increased. Authors and processing software need to clearly
			distinguish between metadata and content. This is not always possible to tell from the
			element names or positions. It is better to provide a context that will disambiguate the
			types of data. Obviously the first step in using this pattern is to be able to identify
			the difference between metadata and data. This is not always an easy task.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para><xref xl:href="metadata-doc.xml" /> and <xref xl:href="head-body.xml" /> are specializations of this pattern.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>

		<para>The W3C Namespace Recommendation includes namespace information in attributes that
			make it clearer that this is data about the documents, and not really part of the
			document itself.</para>
		<para>The XHTML DTD uses <tag class="element">Head</tag> and <tag class="element">Body</tag> elements to distinguish the metadata from the
			data.</para>
	</section>
</section>
