<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	
	version="5.0"
	xreflabel="Metadata in Separate Document"
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Metadata in Separate Document</title>
		
		<abstract>
			<para>When there is a large amount of metadata for a document it can make sense to separate
				this into a different document altogether, with its own document type.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>There may a large amount of metadata for a document. If much of this data is required,
			it could make the document difficult to author and read.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>There is a large amount of metadata to be associated with the documents. If the
			metadata for several documents is the same.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>Metadata can add complexity to a document, making it more difficult to author a
			document. When processing documents, the metadata may not be needed by some programs.
			Having the metadata in the document can increase processing time.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>

		<para>Place the metadata in the separate document. This document should have its own
			document type. There is a link placed in the document that refers to the metadata
			document.</para>
		<para>If the metadata for several documents is the same, this can be a very good pattern to
			use. If, for example, a document requires extensive biographical information about its
			authors, and several of the documents are by the same author, the single metadata
			document can be used to minimize replication and ease maintenance.</para>
		<para>External parsed entities parsed entities can be used in a similar way, but the
			document type of the original document does not get simplified.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>
		<para>Here is an example that references author information from an external file.</para>

		<example>
			<title><filename>author-info.xml</filename></title>
			
			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Author>
	<Name>Robert Smith</Name>
	<BirthDate>21-04-1960</BirthDate>
	<Address>123 Maple Street</Address>
</Author>
			]]></programlisting>
		</example>


		<example>
			<title><filename>document.xml</filename></title>

			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<!DOCTYPE DOCUMENT[
	<!ENTITY author-info SYSTEM "author-info.xml">
]>
<Document>
	<Head>
		&author-info;
	</Head>
	<Body>
		This is the document.
	</Body>
</Document>
			]]></programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>This pattern makes the separation between the data and the metadata very clear, very
			little confusion can be made between the data and metadata.</para>
		<para>The metadata and data can be defined at different times in the development cycle,
			allowing for iterative development, or for different authors to work on the data and
			metadata at the same time.</para>
		<para>By having the metadata in a separate document, many documents can include the metadata
			from the same source. In the Example above, if the address of the author had changed,
			all of the documents which included this document would be automatically changed as
			well.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>This is a specialization of both the the <xref xl:href="matadata-data.xml" /> and
			<uri xl:href="#">FIXME</uri> patterns.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>
		<para>…</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>References</title>
		<para>See: The XML &amp; SGML Cookbook page 2–23.</para>
	</section>
</section>
