<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	version="5.0"
	
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Short Understandable Names</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>Names of elements and attributes should short and understandable by authors and
				developers of processing software.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>

	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>Names need to be given to each attribute and name.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>This pattern can be used in any document type. All documents have named elements and
			attributes.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>Shorter names make the authoring of documents easier and reduces the overall length of
			documents. Names that are too short make the document difficult to understand.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Use names that are long enough to convey the meaning of the document to its intended
			audience, but are short enough to be typed easily. Similar naming length issues are seen
			in programming languages.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>
		<para>A element name such as TelephoneDescription is fairly long, PhoneDescription or
			PhoneDesc might be more appropriate choices.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>Use well known terms and abbreviations from the domain that the document deals with.
			These terms and abbreviations should be used consistently throughout the document. The
			audience of the document must be kept in mind, too much jargon can intimidate novices
			very quickly.</para>
		<para>Context can be take into account to shorten names as well. In the following
			sample:</para>


		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Telephone>
	<TelephoneModelName>X-259</TelephoneModelName>
</Telephone>
           ]]></programlisting>


		<para>The element name TelephoneModelName could easily be shortened to ModelName without
			loosing any understandability of the document.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>…</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>
		<para>HTML uses many element names which are shortened beyond understandability, for example
			the b, i, dt, and ul elements are very cryptic to novice users. Element names such as
			font and img convey much more meaning, and are not long enough to cause problems.</para>
	</section>
</section>