<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	version="5.0"
	
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Declare Before First Use</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>Elements which are referenced by another part of a document should be found earlier in
				the document than the first place they are referenced.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>Often an element will refer to another one; this is what the ID and IDREF attributes
			in XML are used for. A common example is a footnote element. When processing software
			encounters an reference to an element that has not yet been processed, it often has to
			do more processing.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>This pattern applies to a wide variety of document types. It is common to have
			elements reference one another.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>Ease of processing is effected by element order. Having elements in the correct order
			can make processing easier.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Ensure that the elements are ordered so that elements are encountered before they are
			referred to. This gives the processing software a better chance of doing a single pass
			traversal of the document.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>

		<literallayout language="xml dtd">
&lt;!DOCTYPE Doc [

&lt;!ELEMENT Person (Adress*, BillToAddress, ShipToAddress)&gt;

&lt;!ELEMENT Address (#PCDATA)&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST Address id IDREF #REQUIRED &gt;

&lt;!ELEMENT BillToAddress EMPTY&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST BillToAddress address IDREF #REQUIRED&gt;

&lt;!ELEMENT ShipToAddress EMPTY&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST ShipToAddress address IDREF #REQUIRED&gt;

]&gt;

&lt;Doc&gt;
&lt;Person&gt;
&lt;Address id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
123 Main St, New York NY
&lt;/Address&gt;
&lt;Address id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
2001 5th Ave, New York NY
&lt;/Address&gt;
&lt;BillToAddress address=&quot;1&quot;/&gt;
&lt;ShipToAddress address=&quot;2&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/Person&gt;
&lt;/Doc&gt;
</literallayout>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>
		<para>Stream based processors are popular, particularly when documents are very large, and
			may take up large amounts of memory, or when speed of processing is essential. It is
			often difficult to use stream based processing if elements that are needed to process a
			section of the document do not appear until after the place they are needed. This
			requires a forward-looking mechanism that goes against the principle of stream based
			processing.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>Consider this pattern when applying the <link xl:href="/patterns/organization/referenced-note.xml">Referenced Note</link>. The <link xl:href="/patterns/metadata/metadata-first.xml">Metadata First</link> is very
			similar to this patterns, except it deals with metadata instead of general elements as
			this pattern does.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>
		<para>…</para>
	</section>
</section>
