<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	version="5.0"
	
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Envelope</title>

		<abstract>
			<title>Abstract</title>
			<para>Provide a document type which is defined to be a holder for other, arbitrary XML
				data.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>Different sets of data need to be delivered to a system in a consistent way.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>This pattern applies when different sets of data need to be used in some system. The
			structure of the data itself varies, or is not known at the time the system is being
			built.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>

		<para>This pattern allows for Flexibility by allowing elements from other documents to be
			embedded into a consistent holder.</para>
		<para>This pattern allows for a separation of concerns between different document types.
			Mixing issues such as transport with document data is usually not a good idea.</para>
	</section>


	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Create a document type which will act as a holder for the varying set of data.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>

		<para>This example shows a very simple <link xl:href="/patterns/organization/envelope.xml">Envelope</link> which consists of sender and a receiver
			children elements. Note the use of two different namespaces to allow an XML parser to
			read the document, which contains elements from both the <link xl:href="/patterns/organization/envelope.xml">Envelope</link> (<link xl:href="/patterns/organization/envelope.xml"><filename>Envelope.dtd</filename></link>) and the
			embedded data.</para>

		<example>
		    <title><filename>my-stuff.dtd</filename></title>
		    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<e:Envelope xmlsns:e="http://xmlpatterns.com/envelope.dtd">
	<e:sender name="bob"/>
	<e:receiver name="http://xmlpatterns.com/message-receiver.cgi"/>
	
	<myStuff:message xmlsns:e="http://xmlpatterns.com/my-stuff.dtd">
		This is my message
	</myStuff:message>
</e:Envelope>
		]]></programlisting></example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>
		<para>The <link xl:href="/patterns/organization/envelope.xml">Envelope</link> is used as a delivery mechanism for XML data. Document types created for
			holding domain data should not be responsible, for defining transport ways to do deal
			with things such as transport, security, delivery and packaging. The <link xl:href="/patterns/organization/envelope.xml">Envelope</link> provide
			for a clear separation between these things and the data itself.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>This is similar to the <link xl:href="/patterns/flexibility/catch-all.xml">Catch-All Element</link>, except that the the document type of the
			<link xl:href="/patterns/organization/envelope.xml">Envelope</link> pattern exists solely as an holder for other data and, the <link xl:href="/patterns/flexibility/catch-all.xml">Catch-All Element</link> is
			for embedding new elements within exsisting data.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>
		<para><acronym>SOAP</acronym> (Simple Object Access Protocol) is an <link xl:href="/patterns/organization/envelope.xml">Envelope</link> for doing remote transport of
			messages.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>References</title>
		<para>…</para>
	</section>

</section>
