<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	version="5.0"
	
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
 		<title>Flyweight</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>If the same information is included at many different points in a document the
				information can be placed in just one place, and shared from each place in the document
				that needs to refer to it.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>

	
	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>

		<para>Placing the same information in many different place can cause several
			problems:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Mistakes can be made in copying the information</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If the data changes, all occurrences of the information must be located and
					changed. This makes maintenance of the document difficult.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Documents can become quite large if the same information is repeated over and
					over again.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Context</title>

		<para>This is a very general pattern, almost any document type can make use of it. This
			pattern can be used anywhere where the same information must be repeated more than once
			in a document. The repeated data can occur in the document declaration, or in the
			document instance itself.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>

		<para>This pattern can effect the length of the document, maintainability, and readability
			of the document.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>

		<para>Place the shared information in just one place, and make references to it from every
			place in the document that needs to include this information. There are several ways to
			do this:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use XML Entity Declarations. These provide a way to do text substitutions
					inside of a document. The XML Specification Section 4.2 Entity
					Declarations</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use the XLink attribute xlink:show=&quot;embed&quot;. This technique has the
					advantage of using a standard, so some tools may be available to do the
					processing. This is defined in The W3C’s XML Linking Language
					Specification</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use ID and IDREF attributes. A reference can be made to an entity via an IDREF
					attribute. Applications processing this will need to do the processing to do
					this type of Flyweight.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>See the Examples section for an example of each of the above techniques.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>
		<example>
			<title>XML Entities</title>
			<para>This example shows how XML Entities can be used to put a piece of information in
				just one place, and then have it appear in multiple places in the document.</para>

			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<!DOCTYPE Doc[
	<!ENTITY TITLE "My Document">
]>
<Document>
	<title>&TITLE;</title>
	<H1>&TITLE;</H1>

	This is my paragraph.
</Document>
			]]></programlisting>
		</example>
		
		<example>
			<title>XLink</title>
			<para>This document shows the use of XLink attributes to include the contents of a
				document in two different places. Since XLink is a standard it is possible that
				existing tools could be used to do the substitution.</para>

			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Document>
	<title>
		<include xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="titledoc.txt"/>
	</title>
	
	<h1>
		<include xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="titledoc.txt"/>
	</h1>
	
	This is my paragraph.
</Document>
]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<example>
			<title>ID and IDREF</title>
			<para>This shows how ID and IDREF attributes can be used as a Flyweight. Note thats this
				would require some extra work on the part of the processing software to do the
				substitution.</para>

			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[                              
<Document>
	<text id="title">My Document</text>
	<title IDREF="title"/>

	<h1 IDREF="title"/>
</Document>
			]]></programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>This pattern can greatly enhance the maintainability of a document, if the same data
			is repeated several times, and that data changes, every occurrence of that data must be
			found and updated. This can be a tedious and error prone task. Having the data in only
			one place allows all occurrences of it to be changed at once.</para>
		<para>The Flyweight pattern should not be used if the shared information can vary over time.
			This would increase the maintenance burden of the document.</para>
		<para>Readability of the document can suffer if the Flyweight pattern is used, readers are
			forced to reference a different section of the document when looking at the
			contents.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>See <link xl:href="/patterns/metadata/declare-before.xml">Declare Before First Use</link> for suggestions on where to place the shared
			information.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>

		<para>XHTML uses a a <link xl:href="/patterns/consistency/common-attributes.xml">Common Attributes</link> parameter entity that is a Flyweight.</para>
		<para>The XML &amp; SGML Cookbook page 1–126 mentions the Flyweight pattern.</para>
	</section>
</section>