<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	
	version="5.0"
    xreflabel="Referenced Note"
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Referenced Note</title>

		<abstract>
			<title>Abstract</title>
			<para>When an area in text needs to refer to a note that will be placed in a different part
				of the document, a reference is made to a separate entity using an <tag class="attribute">IDREF</tag>.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>


	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>Some text needs to make a reference to another piece of text that is located elsewhere
			with the original text. This could be a footnote, an annotation, or an endnote. The
			position of the note in the final document will not be known until the document is
			rendered.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>Notes occur when a comment needs to be made about a piece of text, but the author does
			not want the main text flow to be interrupted. This is a very publication oriented
			pattern, it is not as relevant in data interchange documents.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>Ease of Use and Ease of Processing is effected by how a note is organized.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>

		<para>The note is put in a element which is not contained within the flow of the text where
			the note is referenced from. An attribute of type <tag class="attribute">ID</tag> is put 
		    on the <tag class="element">note</tag> element, and an element is inserted into the flow 
		    of the text with an <tag class="attribute">IDREF</tag> that refers to the 
		    <tag class="element">note</tag>’s <tag class="attribute">ID</tag>. A different 
		    solution would be to simply use an inline element to include the note as such:</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Paragraph>This paragraph refers to a note.
	
	<Note>This is the note.</Note>

</Paragraph>
]]></programlisting>


		<para>This solution has a couple of potential disadvantages:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The <tag class="element">note</tag> cannot be referred to from more than one place.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The <tag class="element">note</tag> is not physically removed from the text in the marked up document. It
					may more difficult for the author of the document to realize how the note will
					be used in the published form of the document.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>


		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Paragraph>
	This paragraph refers to a note.
	
	<NoteReference ref="1"/>
</Paragraph>

<Note id="1">This is the note.</Note>
]]></programlisting>


		<para>When rendered the document could be made to look like this:</para>

		<programlisting language="text"><![CDATA[
This paragraph refers to a note.
1
… rest of page …

1: This is a note.

…end of page
]]></programlisting>
	</section>


	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>Using this pattern can lead to easier to use documents. Since authors expect notes to
			be separated from the flow of text, this pattern can lead to more natural mark
			up.</para>
		<para>Rendering software can be simplified if the notes are declared before they will be
			used. For example if the note is to go on the bottom of a page, the rendering software
			can calculate page breaks on the fly if the size of the note is already known when the
			reference to it is encountered.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>

		<para>This is an example of a Domain Element from the publishing world.</para>
		<para>Also consider using <link xl:href="/patterns/metadata/declare-before.xml">Declare Before First Use</link> with this pattern.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>
		<para>…</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>References</title>
		<para>This is a generalization of: Footnote Pattern on the The XML Specification Guide web
			site.</para>
	</section>
</section>
