<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	version="5.0"
	
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Generic Element</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>To provide flexibility to users of the document, designers can provide an element
				type that is very generic. The use of the Generic Element is not well specified by
				the documents type. This allows for authors to use the document type in ways that
				may not have been foreseen.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>

	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>The designer does not know exactly what the users of the document intend to do with
			the document and needs to add flexibility to the document type.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>This is useful in general purpose document types, when flexibility is needed.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>Flexibility is required to make some document types useful. This pattern can effect
			the ease of processing of the document type.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Provide a new element that does not have a specific meaning.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<Paragraph>
	Albert Camus' <General type="book">The Stranger</General> is an existentialist novel.
</Paragraph>
]]></programlisting>
	</section>


	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>Not providing enough flexibility can make document authors use the wrong element for
			markup. This can lead to documents that are difficult to understand, and mistakes in
			processing occur.</para>
		<para>This flexibility can make processing software difficult to create. Adding Role
			Attributes to the Generic Element can help provide the processing software some clues as
			to how to process the element.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>A <link xl:href="/patterns/flexibility/role.xml">Role Attribute</link> is often used in conjunction with Generic Elements.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>
		<para>The div and span elements in XHTML.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>References</title>
		<para>The Fielded Text example from The XML &amp; SGML Cookbook page 2–48, uses Generic
			Elements.</para>
	</section>

</section>
