<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	
	version="5.0"
	xreflabel="Common Attributes"
	role="pattern">
	
	<info>
		<title>Common Attributes</title>

		<abstract>
			<para>Provide a set of attributes that can be placed on all, or most, elements in the document type.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>

	<section>
		<title>Problem</title>
		<para>There are properties that belong to every element in the document. These properties
			need to be presented to the document author in an understandable way.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Context</title>
		<para>This is a widely applicable pattern and can be used anywhere that a large number of
			elements need the same attributes applied. It is a common technique for attributes such
			as IDs, security, and roles.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Forces</title>
		<para>The usability of the document type depends a lot on consistency, and this pattern can
			be used to add consistency.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Solution</title>
		<para>Create a common set of attributes that will be used by all or most of the elements in
			the document type.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Examples</title>

		<example>
			<title>Common Attributes in DTDs</title>
			<para>This examples shows a DTD that has two <link xl:href="/patterns/consistency/common-attributes.xml">Common Attributes</link>, id and role, on its all
				of its elements. The common attribute definition is placed in a parameter entity
				which is referenced by all of the ATTLIST definitions.</para>



			<programlisting language="dtd"><![CDATA[
<!ENTITY % common.att
	'id   ID      #IMPLIED
	role NMTOKEN #IMPLIED'>

<!ELEMENT Person (FirstName, LastName)>
<!ATTLIST Person %common.att;>

<!ELEMENT FirstName (#PCDATA)>
<!ATTLIST FirstName %common.att;>

<!ELEMENT LastName (#PCDATA)>
<!ATTLIST LastName %common.att;>
                ]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<example>
			<title>Common Attributes in XML Schemas</title>
			<para>This example shows how to implement the same document structure as the above
				examples using the XSL Schema language Attributes Groups .</para>

			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<schema xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/XMLSchema"
		targetNamespace="http://www.xmlpatterns.com/XMLSchema-fragment"
		xmlns:xsf="http://www.xmlpatterns.com/XMLSchema-fragment">

    <attributeGroup name="CommonAtts">
        <attribute name="id" type="ID"/>
        <attribute name="role" type="NMTOKEN"/>
    </attributeGroup>
    
    <complexType name="NameType">
        <attributeGroup ref="CommonAtts"/>
    </complexType>
    
    <complexType name="PersonType" content="elementOnly">
        <element name="FirstName" type="xsf:NameType"/>
        <element name="LastName" type="xsf:NameType"/>
        <attributeGroup ref="CommonAtts"/>
    </complexType>
    
    <element name="Person" type="xsf:PersonType"/>

</schema>
                ]]></programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>



	<section>
		<title>Discussion</title>

		<para>Global attributes often add many choices at any point in the document. Users have more
			selections available to them, and this could complicate authoring, however, some of the
			complexity that adding attributes to every element brings is lessened if these
			attributes are applied consistently. If users can expect the same common attribute on
			every element, it does not take a lot of extra effort to process the information. It
			will be easier to author or process a document that has a consistently applied set of
			Common Attributes on all elements compared to one that has inconsistently applied
			attributes on most of the elements.</para>
		<para>An ID attribute is a typical use for a common attribute. It is useful to be able to
			reference any element in the document using this.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Related Patterns</title>
		<para>The Common Attributes are usually declared in a <xref xl:href="../organization/flyweight.xml" /> to help maintainability.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Known Uses</title>

		<para>The XMLspec DTD Common Attributes Chapter explains the use of Common Attributes in the DTD.</para>
		<para>
		    XHTML defines a set of core attributes. 
		    These attributes are applied to almost every element in the XHTML document type. 
			The core attributes are defined like this:</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<!ENTITY % coreattrs
	"id     ID           #IMPLIED
	class  CDATA        #IMPLIED
	style  %StyleSheet; #IMPLIED
	title  %Text;       #IMPLIED"
>
		]]></programlisting>


		<para>Even the simple line break element has these attributes added to it:</para>

		<programlisting language="dtd"><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT br EMPTY>  <!-- forced line break -->
<!ATTLIST br
	%coreattrs;
>
         ]]></programlisting>
	</section>




	<section>
		<title>References</title>
		<para>See Structuring XML Documents, Section 3.2.4: Global Attributes.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Contributions</title>
		<para>Thanks to Hans C. Arents for supplying the correct XSL Schema definition used in the
			pattern.</para>
	</section>
</section>
